[
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the digital transaction banking platform launched by Federal Bank for corporate and SME customers on January 2, 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Fedone",
      "Fed anytime",
      "Fed Everywhere",
      "Both 1 and 2",
      "Do Fed Every Time"
    ],
    "answer": "Fedone"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country received $5 lakh relief assistance from India for rehabilitation after a 7.4 magnitude earthquake in December 2024?",
    "options": [
      "Tonga",
      "Fiji",
      "Samoa",
      "Vanuatu",
      "Kiribati"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the amount approved by the Cabinet Committee on Economic Affairs (CCEA) for the revival of Rashtriya Ispat Nigam Limited (RINL)?",
    "options": [
      "₹11,440 crore",
      "₹10,500 crore",
      "₹12,090 crore",
      "₹9,950 crore",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "₹11,440 crore"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is India's current rank in terms of the largest metro network in the world?",
    "options": [
      "First",
      "Second",
      "Third",
      "Fourth",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which contingent won the Best Marching Contingent (CAPFs/auxiliary forces) in the People's Choice Category during the Republic Day Parade 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Delhi Police Marching Contingent",
      "BSF Marching Contingent",
      "CRPF Marching Contingent",
      "ITBP Marching Contingent",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been given the additional charge as Secretary of the Ministry of New and Renewable Energy (MNRE)? (Jan 2025)",
    "options": [
      "Alok Ranjan",
      "Nidhi Khare",
      "Rajiv Singh",
      "Preeti Sharma",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the primary purpose of the RBI's decision to infuse Rs 1.1 lakh crore liquidity into the banking system?",
    "options": [
      "To provide immediate credit growth to banks",
      "To manage liquidity challenges and stabilize the banking system",
      "To finance upcoming government infrastructure projects",
      "To increase interest rates across financial markets",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "To manage liquidity challenges and stabilize the banking system"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Open Network for Digital Commerce (ONDC) initiative was incorporated as a non-profit, Section-8 company and incubated at the ______.",
    "options": [
      "NITI Aayog",
      "Quality Council of India",
      "Reserve Bank of India",
      "Ministry of Commerce and Industry",
      "National Informatics Centre"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been appointed Director of the Liquid Propulsion Systems Centre (LPSC) in January 2025?",
    "options": [
      "S. Somanath",
      "R. Umamaheswaran",
      "P. Kunhikrishnan",
      "M. Mohan",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which traditional Bosnian art form was added to UNESCO's National Inventory of Intangible Cultural Heritage in December 2024?",
    "options": [
      "Sevdalinka",
      "Flamenco",
      "Bharatanatyam",
      "Tango",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Sevdalinka"
  },
  {
    "question": "India ranks 4th in the Global Firepower Index 2025. Which country tops the Global Firepower Index 2025?",
    "options": [
      "China",
      "Russia",
      "USA",
      "Germany",
      "Pakistan"
    ],
    "answer": "USA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been appointed as the Director General (DG) of the Directorate General of Civil Aviation (DGCA) as of January 3, 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Vikram Dev Dutt",
      "Dinesh Chand Sharma",
      "Faiz Ahmed Kidwai",
      "Rajiv Bansal",
      "Arun Kumar"
    ],
    "answer": "Faiz Ahmed Kidwai"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the projected real GDP growth rate for India in FY25 according to the National Statistics Office (NSO)?",
    "options": [
      "8.2%",
      "6.4%",
      "7.2%",
      "5.5%",
      "5.9%"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the key objective of the Aircraft Leasing Bill approved by the Indian government in 2024?",
    "options": [
      "To introduce new airlines in India, thereby making the airline market more competitive",
      "To build new aircraft manufacturing facilities in India via international collaboration",
      "To increase regressive tax benefits for airline operators.",
      "To reduce airfares by lowering leasing and financing costs for airlines.",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "To reduce airfares by lowering leasing and financing costs for airlines."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which state signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) with the State Bank of India (SBI) and Union Bank of India (UBI) to offer insurance benefits to its government employees on January 1, 2025?",
    "options": [
      "West Bengal",
      "Assam",
      "Odisha",
      "Bihar",
      "Jharkhand"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "On January 13, 2025, the rupee experienced its steepest drop in two years, closing at ________ against the dollar.",
    "options": [
      "₹83.45",
      "₹84.51",
      "₹85.60",
      "₹86.58",
      "₹88.40"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who will be the Chief Guest at India's 76th Republic Day celebrations in 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Australian Prime Minister",
      "Indonesian President",
      "Canadian Prime Minister",
      "UK Prime Minister",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been reappointed as Ireland's Prime Minister (Taoiseach) for the second time in January 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Micheál Martin",
      "Enda Kenny",
      "Leo Varadkar",
      "Mary Lou McDonald",
      "Laurie Brentford"
    ],
    "answer": "Micheál Martin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been sworn in as the 25th Governor of Mizoram? (Jan 2025)",
    "options": [
      "Anil Chauhan",
      "V K Singh",
      "Arvind Kumar",
      "Manoj Sinha",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been appointed as an independent observer for Chandigarh's mayoral election on January 30?",
    "options": [
      "Justice (retd) Jaishree Thakur",
      "Justice (retd) Kurian Joseph",
      "Justice (retd) Deepak Gupta",
      "Justice (retd) Madan Lokur",
      "None of the abocve"
    ],
    "answer": "Justice (retd) Jaishree Thakur"
  },
  {
    "question": "How much did UPI process in terms of transactions in December 2024?",
    "options": [
      "10 billion transactions",
      "16.73 billion transactions",
      "20.51 billion transactions",
      "25.24 billion transactions",
      "32.19 billion transactions"
    ],
    "answer": "16.73 billion transactions"
  },
  {
    "question": "The State Bank of India (SBI) launched a TAB-based online facility for opening which types of accounts for Non-Resident Indians (NRIs) on January 2, 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Current Account and Savings Account",
      "Fixed Deposit and Recurring Deposit",
      "Non-Resident External (NRE) and Non-Resident Ordinary (NRO) Accounts",
      "Demat Account and Trading Account",
      "Foreign Currency Non-Resident (FCNR) Account"
    ],
    "answer": "Non-Resident External (NRE) and Non-Resident Ordinary (NRO) Accounts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been appointed as the Ombudsman and Ethics Officer of the Board of Control for Cricket in India? (January 2025)",
    "options": [
      "Sourav Ganguly",
      "Justice Arun Mishra",
      "Prabhtej Singh Bhatia",
      "Devajit Saikia",
      "Jay Shah"
    ],
    "answer": "Justice Arun Mishra"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following e-auction portals was launched by Nagaraju Maddirala, Secretary of the Department of Financial Services (DFS), on January 3, 2025?",
    "options": [
      "E-BidNet",
      "BAANKNET",
      "AssetMart",
      "BidConnect",
      "AuctionLink"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the Pakistani satellite launched into space by China in January 2025?",
    "options": [
      "PRSC-EO1",
      "PRSS-1",
      "PakTES-1A",
      "Tianlu-1",
      "Noor-07"
    ],
    "answer": "PRSC-EO1"
  },
  {
    "question": "The newly inaugurated Sonamarg Tunnel by PM Modi ensures all-weather road connectivity between which two locations in Jammu and Kashmir?",
    "options": [
      "Gagangeer and Sonamarg",
      "Srinagar and Leh",
      "Sonamarg and Kargil",
      "Jammu and Sonamarg",
      "Srinagar and Sonamarg"
    ],
    "answer": "Gagangeer and Sonamarg"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which bank launched the 'Har Ghar Lakhpati Recurring Deposit (RD) scheme' and the 'SBI Patrons Fixed Deposit (FD) scheme' on January 3, 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Punjab National Bank",
      "State Bank of India",
      "Bank of Baroda",
      "Bank of Mahrashtra",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which team won the inaugural Women's Hockey India League title?",
    "options": [
      "JSW Soorma Hockey Club",
      "Haryana Strikers",
      "Odisha Warriors",
      "Punjab Panthers",
      "None of the abocve"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "On January 1, 2025, which organization celebrated its 67th Foundation Day in New Delhi?",
    "options": [
      "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)",
      "Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO)",
      "Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL)",
      "Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL)",
      "Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC)"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the Oxfam report, how much wealth was extracted from India by the UK between 1765 and 1900, in today's value?",
    "options": [
      "$64.82 trillion",
      "$33.8 trillion",
      "$50 trillion",
      "$2 trillion",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "$64.82 trillion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the first Artificial and Emotional Intelligence-driven fashion forecasting platform, developed under the Ministry of Textiles?",
    "options": [
      "TextYle AI",
      "EnVision",
      "Parikalpna AI",
      "VisioNxt",
      "DeepSeek"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been honoured with the RK Srikantan Trust Award at the Sankranti Music Festival in Bengaluru?",
    "options": [
      "L. Subramaniam",
      "TV Gopalakrishnan",
      "Zakir Hussain",
      "Ravi Shankar",
      "Shankar Mahajan"
    ],
    "answer": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which start-up successfully tested UHF communication technology via SwetchaSat on ISRO's POEM-4 platform?",
    "options": [
      "N Space Tech",
      "SkyTech Innovations",
      "AstroSpace Pvt. Ltd.",
      "NovaSat Systems",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "N Space Tech"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Ministry of Youth Affairs and Sports has announced the National Sports Awards 2024. Four sportspersons have been conferred with the Major Dhyan Chand Khel Ratna Award. Who among the following is not one of the four sportspersons?",
    "options": [
      "Praveen Kumar",
      "Manu Bhaker",
      "Gukesh D",
      "Harmanpreet Singh",
      "Sucha Singh"
    ],
    "answer": "5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been appointed as the Director General of the Bureau of Police Research and Development (BPR&D) in January 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Barinder Jeet Singh",
      "Neeru Garg",
      "P Renuka Devi",
      "Senthil Avudai Krishna Raj S",
      "Brajesh Punia"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which app was launched by Defence Minister Rajnath Singh during the 77th Army Day celebrations to promote battlefield tourism?",
    "options": [
      "Bharat Raksha App",
      "Military Heritage App",
      "Bharat Ranbhoomi Darshan App",
      "Siachen War Memorial App",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the title of the legislation recently passed by the US House to bar transgender athletes from women's sports at federally funded schools, defining sex by birth biology?",
    "options": [
      "Equality in Athletics Act",
      "Protection of Women and Girls in Sports Act",
      "Fair Play in Sports Act",
      "Women's Sports Equity Act",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who launched Phase 4 of the National Educational Alliance for Technology (NEAT 4.0) in January 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Ministry of Education",
      "University Grants Commission (UGC)",
      "All India Council for Technical Education (AICTE)",
      "National Board of Accreditation (NBA)",
      "National Testing Agency (NTA)"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the projected growth rate for India's economy over the next two fiscal years (2025-2027) according to the World Bank?",
    "options": [
      "6.3%",
      "6.5%",
      "6.7%",
      "7.2%",
      "7.7%"
    ],
    "answer": "6.7%"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the name of the indigenously developed docking system used by ISRO to successfully dock satellites SDX01 and SDX02?",
    "options": [
      "Bhartiya Docking System",
      "PSLV Docking System",
      "Gaganyaan Docking System",
      "Chandrayaan Docking System",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Bhartiya Docking System"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the recipient of the Gangadhar National Award for Poetry 2023?",
    "options": [
      "Sitakant Mahapatra",
      "Prativa Satpathy",
      "Jayanta Mahapatra",
      "Ramakanta Rath",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which forum did Piyush Goyal launch the 'Bharat Cleantech Manufacturing Platform,' aimed at boosting solar, wind, hydrogen, and battery sectors, and positioning India as a global leader in clean energy manufacturing?",
    "options": [
      "Bharat Sustainability Summit",
      "Bharat Climate Forum 2025",
      "India Renewable Energy Forum",
      "Global Green Energy Summit",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Nag Mk 2, a _____-generation Fire-and-Forget Anti-Tank Guided Missile, successfully completed field trials at Pokhran Field Range, achieving targets at both maximum and minimum ranges.",
    "options": [
      "2nd",
      "3rd",
      "4th",
      "5th",
      "6th"
    ],
    "answer": "3rd"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which report stated that India's poverty rate fell below 5% in 2024, with rural poverty at 4.86% and urban poverty at 4.09%?",
    "options": [
      "RBI Report",
      "NITI Aayog Report",
      "SBI Report",
      "Ministry of Finance Report",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "SBI Report"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which year has the Ministry of Defence designated as the 'Year of Reforms' to modernize the Armed Forces?",
    "options": [
      "2023",
      "2024",
      "2025",
      "2026",
      "2027"
    ],
    "answer": "2025"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the author of the book \"Parliament: Powers, Functions & Privileges\"?",
    "options": [
      "Dr. P.C. Mody",
      "Dr. Devendra Singh Chauhan",
      "Justice Kaul",
      "Shri Rajya Sabha Secretary General",
      "Prof. Sanjay Mehrotra"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under which scheme has the Rural Development Ministry approved 56 watershed development projects worth ₹700 crore, covering approximately 2.8 lakh hectares across 10 states?",
    "options": [
      "MGNREGA",
      "National Water Mission",
      "Soil Health Management Scheme",
      "PMKSY-WDC 2.0",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country is experiencing an outbreak of human metapneumovirus (HMPV)?",
    "options": [
      "Indonesia",
      "China",
      "Japan",
      "South Korea",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where was the foundation stone for the new Central Ayurveda Research Institute building laid by PM Modi?",
    "options": [
      "Bengaluru",
      "Mumbai",
      "New Delhi",
      "Hyderabad",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where was the closing event of the \"Hamara Samvidhan Hamara Swabhiman\" campaign organized?",
    "options": [
      "Haridwar",
      "Nashik",
      "Prayagraj",
      "Rishikesh",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "In September 2024, India surpassed which milestone in renewable energy capacity?",
    "options": [
      "100 GW",
      "150 GW",
      "200 GW",
      "250 GW",
      "300 GW"
    ],
    "answer": "200 GW"
  }
]